Music
Music
rate
rate
The important activities of the school to promote science popularization have been going on for many years. Every month, there are forests, biology, humanities, and mountain masters. Scholars and experts from inside and outside the hospital are invited to watch.
本院推广科普的重要活动行之有年,每个月都有分别是树林,生物,人文,山主,轮流,请院内外的学者专家来看。
We are very happy and honored today
今天我們非常高興也非常榮幸
Please go to the Humanities and Social Sciences Research Center of our hospital
請到本院人文社會科學研究中心的
Dr. Xiao Gaoyuan came to talk to you
蕭高院博士來跟大家談
Is democracy a universal value
民主是普遍價值嗎
Dr. Hsiao is a member of the Department of Political Science, National Taiwan University
蕭博士是台灣大學政治系
Graduated from Political Science Institute
政治研究所畢業
Then went to Yale University for Ph.D.
然後到耶魯大學獲得博士
After I came back, I was at the Academia Sinica
回來之後就在中央研究院的
Zhongshan Institute of Humanities and Social Sciences Cognitive
中山人文社會科學研究所認知
Later, after Zhongshan Humanities and Social Sciences was changed to the Center for Humanities and Social Sciences
後來中山人文社科學改成人文社中心以後
he's always there
他一直都在那裡
Currently a researcher at the institute
目前是該所的研究員
Bing is also the executive director of the Research Center for Political Thought
兵兼政治思想研究專題中心的執行長
At the same time, he is also the member of the academic executive committee of the college.
同時他也是院的學術執行總會的
deputy executive secretary
副執行秘書
Professor Xiao's field of research is
蕭教授的這個研究領域是
History of Western Political Thought and Contemporary Political Philosophy
西方政治思想史以及當代政治哲學
His doctoral dissertation was dealing with
他的博士論文是處理
Hegel's Ethics and Politics
黑格爾的倫理政治論
China's early research on contemporary political theory issues
國初期研究當代政治理論議題
communitarianism
如社群主義
and related issues of social identity in Taiwan
以及這些論述以台灣社會認同的相關問題
In a short time after Professor Xiao returned to China
蕭教授在回國以後很短的時間
Just because an article was published in the most important political science journal in the West
就因為有一篇文章登在西方最重要的政治學刊物
Contact Award from the National Science Council
而得到國科會的接觸獎
I was told so far
有人告訴我到目前為止
There are only three articles published by domestic scholars in that journal
本國的學者也只有三篇文章登在那個刊物
Well, this is the first time I heard the name of Professor Xiao
那麼這個是我最早聽到蕭教授的名字的
In the past ten years or so, he has started with the history of thought and political analysis
最近十多年他以思想史以及政治學分析起象
Research on the historical evolution and theoretical significance of Western republicanism
研究西方共和主義的歷史演進及理論意義
There is already a book of five or six hundred pages that will be published by a certain publishing house soon
已經有一部五六百頁的書很快就會在某出版社出版
What about Professor Xiao?
那麼蕭教授呢
Because he is here today, I dare not speak too exaggerated language
因為他今天在所以我不敢講太誇張的語言
Well, if he's not here, I'm going to say
那麼如果他不在呢我就要說
He's actually a lot of people who have told me
他事實上是很多人跟我講過
He is our most important student of the history of Western political thought
他是我們最重要的西方政治思想史的學生
loud voice he's on so i speak one
大聲音他在 所以我講之一
hope it didn't trouble him
希望沒有給他帶來麻煩
Democracy is one everyone knows
民主是一個人人都知道
But everyone hasn't read a full
但人人都還沒有讀過一本完整的
title of book on democracy and liberty
民主跟自由的書的題目
Originally, the topic of thought was very difficult to talk about.
本來思想方面的題目非常難講
Personally, I never had the courage to speak out.
我個人就一直沒有這個勇氣來講
problems in this area
這方面的問題
because it is a feast of knowledge
因為是一個知識饗宴
talk about things that are too thoughtful and too philosophical
講太思想太哲學的東西
Difficult to hold the audience's attention
很難吸引住觀眾的注意力
but today i believe
不過今天我相信
I hope you have enough attention
希望大家有足夠的注意力
But I think Professor Xiao will be able to complete this task
不過我想蕭教授一定能完成這個任務
Give a successful speech on Western political thought
做一場關於西洋政治思想的成功演講
His topic today is Is Democracy a Universal Value?
他今天的題目是民主是普遍價值嗎
as far as i talked to him earlier
據我先前跟他談
The most important thing for him is to discuss with you
他最重要的是要跟各位討論
How does democracy go from a
民主如何從一個
Turns out there were negative reviews
原來還帶有負面評價的東西
then slowly evolved into
後來慢慢慢慢演變成
Democracy is now a universal value throughout history
現在民主是一個普遍價值的整個歷史
Let's welcome the professor with warm applause
我們先在熱烈的掌聲歡迎一下教授
Thank you, Vice President, Hello, everyone.
謝謝副院長各位來賓大家好
Well I am very happy to have this opportunity today
那麼我很高興今天有這個機會
Let me discuss with you whether this democracy is a universal value.
來跟大家來討論一下這個民主是普遍價值嗎
such a topic
這樣的一個題目
Then what Chen Rufei Yanggang just said
那麼陳如飛揚港剛剛說的
This feast of knowledge is aimed at audiences of many levels
這個知識饗宴是針對很多層次的聽眾
Well, this is actually the first time I've given a public speech
那麼其實這是我第一次做一個比較公共性的演講
So maybe lack of experience
所以經驗上可能不足
Then I will try my best to use Taiwan's experience
那麼我會盡量的用台灣的經驗
And the entry of some ideas of this daily life
以及這個日常生活的一些想法的切入
But there are still a lot of unavoidable content
但是不可免的內容當中還是有不少
This one of my majors
我自己專業之中的這個
That is, hope is really like some concepts in the middle
也就是希望真的是像是中間的一些概念
and an explanation of its rheology
跟它的流變的一個解說
But I hope that after the explanation
但是我希望在解說完畢之後呢
able to have some
能夠有一些可以
We might end up at the end for half an hour
我們最後面可能留個半個小時
Teach Me PowerPoint
教我的PowerPoint
Then I suddenly finished
到後來我突然講完了
that may have more time
那可能有更多的時間的話
we have more time to do a
我們有更多的時間來做一個
a free discussion
自由的一個討論
Then I am for democracy
那麼我對於民主
We only need one now
我們現在只需要一個
very simple one to start with
非常簡單的一個開始
without a very complicated definition
不用非常複雜的一個定義
Democracy in the language of the West
民主在西方的語言當中
It is Demo
它就是Demo
Democracy is Demo and Kratia
Democracy就是Demo跟Kratia
It's the word Kratis
就是Kratis這兩個字
it is a greek
它是一個希臘文
So Demos represent a meaning of the people
那麼Demos代表的是人民的一個意思
Then the word Kratia is basically
那麼Kratia這個字基本上是
Power or Authority
Power或者是Authority
the rights of the people
也就是人民的權利
It represents a right of the people
它代表的是一種人民的權利
or the rule of the people
或者是人民的統治
so its this
所以它的這個
such a definition
這樣的一個定義來講的話
no need
並沒有也不需要
there is a very specific one
有一個非常特定的一個
a sign of the system
制度的一個指色
so so democratic
那麼所以民主
not just for orientals or chinese
不只是對東方人或者是中國人
or Taiwanese
或者是台灣人
When I first came into contact with Western thought
最早期接觸西方思想的時候
or cultural time
或文化的時候
It may be very difficult to imagine the concept of democracy
可能對於民主這個概念是非常難以想像
even if
即使是
even the west itself
即使是西方本身
One thing I want to talk about today is that
我今天特別要來談的一件事情就是說
the concept of democracy
民主這個概念
Well it's not just in the rest of our society
那麼它不只是在我們其他的社會當中
by learning
是通過學習
and interpretation
以及詮釋
and implement it in our local environment
以及在我們在地的環境當中才加以落實
in the western world
在西方的世界
in the history of thought
在思想史當中
and in actual politics
以及在實際的政治當中
It actually went through the same process
它其實也是經歷了相同的一個過程
So democracy is a very special value
所以民主是一個非常特殊的一個價值
then i hope i can today
那麼我希望我今天能夠
take it slow and talk it out
慢慢的把這一點把它談出來
So of course democracy is a universal value
那當然民主是否是一個普遍的價值
this universal value
這個普遍價值
Or sometimes we translate into universal values
或者是有時候我們翻譯成普世價值
Then of course we say that democracy is a universal value
那麼當然我們講民主是一個普遍價值
or a universal value
或者是一個普世價值的意思
it doesn't mean
它並不是說
For example, we say that the force of gravity
比如說我們說萬有引力
is a universal concentration
是一個普遍的定力
not a universal in the sense
不是這個意義底下的一個普遍性
a universal
一個普遍性
but we see now
但是我們現在看
In a current public discourse
當前的一個公共的一個論述當中
so let's say it
那麼我們這麼說好了
that means we would say
就是說我們會說
Values ​​that every rational citizen should accept
每一個理性的公民都應該接受的價值
why i use this quotes
我為什麼用這個引號
or English quotation
或者是英文的 quotation
Because this is contemporary political philosophy
因為這個是當代政治哲學
Some of the more specific ways of expressing
當中一些比較特定的一個表述的方式
it means to say
它的意思就是說
we are talking about democracy
我們在談民主
or when the universality of political values
或者是政治價值的普遍性的時候
we didn't try to make it
我們並沒有要把它做到
scientists or even logic
科學者或者是甚至邏輯學
or a generality in the mathematical sense
或數學上意義上的一個普遍性
but
但是呢
course political philosopher
當然政治哲學家
they will use some different ways
他們會用一些不同的方式
a design for some discourses
一些論述的一個設計
to illustrate that a rational citizen should
來說明一個理性的公民都應該
This should of course be the absolute question right here
這個應該當然絕問就在這個地方
So what about the report I'm waiting for?
那麼我等一下的這個報告當中呢
will speak out slowly
也會慢慢說出來
That is to say, in the long history of democratic thought
就是說在漫長的民主的思想史當中
come and tell us
各種各樣來告訴我們
a reasonable person
一個合理的人
A rational person should accept the democratic
一個理性的人應該接受民主的
Where is the argument for this value
這個價值的論證在什麼地方
So the meaning of a question in my speech
那麼我這個演講的一個問題的意思
like this
是這個樣子
Then the vice president just mentioned briefly
那麼剛才副院長有簡單提一下
Which means we just have to go back and look at history
就是說我們只要回去看歷史
Looking at the context of history
看歷史的脈絡來講的話
We say that democracy has universal values
我們說民主具有普遍的價值
is a very established thing
是一件非常成立的事情
Because human beings in this world have been
因為這個世界上人類從有歷史以來
Almost most people live in
幾乎絕大部分的人都是活在
democracy or aristocracy
民主制度或者是貴族制度
or other systems
或其他的制度當中
or dictatorship
或者是dictatorship
Democratic society in human society
民主的社會在人類的社會當中
Only in the very ancient Greek democracy
只有在非常古代的希臘的民主當中
existed for about two hundred years
存在了大約兩百年
And then when it's seen as after
然後呢當它視為之後
not only in the western world
不但在西方世界
anywhere else in the world
也在世界上其他的任何的地方
except very local
除了非常local的
That is to say, there are some habits of democracy
就是說有一些民主的一些習慣之外
Then when we talk about democratic politics at scale
那麼我們講具有規模的民主政治
does not exist
是不存在的
but it was around the eighteenth century
但是它就在十八世紀左右
began to gradually rise in the context of the West
開始在西方的脈絡當中逐漸興起
Gradually collide
逐漸著撞
until almost the twentieth century
一直到差不多二十世紀
when we were in the second half of the twentieth century
我們在二十世紀的下半夜的時候
Especially the issue of national universality
也就特別是這個民族普遍性這個議題呢
Especially after the collapse of the socialist state
特別是在社會主義的國家瓦解以後的
From the late 1980s to the 1990s
八零年代末期到九零年代的時候
what about that time
那麼那個時候呢
Due to a collapse of this ideology of socialism
由於社會主義的這個意識形態的一個瓦解
Then let the Western world produce a
那麼讓西方的世界產生了一個就是說
OK, in that state
OK 那在那個狀態底下
So is the value of politics already basically
那麼政治的價值是不是已經基本上
In addition to liberal democracy
除了 liberal democracy
That's what they're talking about now I'll talk about it later
就是他們現在我等一下會談到的
A procedural, a liberal democracy, a concept outside
一個程序性的一個自由民主的一個概念之外
Then the ideology that competes with him
那麼跟他競爭的意識形態
Basically it's all gone
基本上都已經喪失了呢
Then such a statement was made in the first half of the night in the 1990s
那麼這樣的一個說法在九零年代上半夜
is very very popular
是非常非常流行的
When I was studying in the United States, there were many discourses on
當我在美國讀書的時候有非常多的論述來
with a very
用一種很
very triumphant tone
很勝利的一個語調
a historical purpose
某種歷史的目的性
Like when I was doing research and Hegel said
像我當年做研究做黑格爾來講
Hegel has a famous saying
黑格爾有一個很有名的一個說法
Said that history is the process of displaying the spirit of freedom
說歷史是自由精神的展現的過程
A very practical statement like this
類似這樣的一個非常行而上的一個論述
in the late 90s
在90年代末期
actually there
居然也在
sorry early 90s
對不起 90年代初期
Also in public forums in the US
也在美國的公共論壇當中
After a package
經過一個包裝之後
Become a human history has reached an end
變成一個人類歷史已經到達一個終點
This end point is beyond Liberal democracy
這個終點就是Liberal democracy之外
it's hard for you to imagine
你大概很難想像
The other value system is the universal one value
其他的價值系統是具有普遍的一個價值
If you know one of those days
假如大家有了解那個時候的一個
words of public discourse
公共論述的話
will know that there is a man named Fukuyama
會知道有一位叫做福克亞馬
Fukuyama Scholars
福山的學者
put forward such an argument
提出來這樣的一個論述
That is a Hegelian language
那是一個以黑格爾的語言
Come to the contemporary forum in the United States
來在美國的當代的論壇當中
when socialism collapsed
就受著社會主義瓦解的時候
Some remarks made
所做的一些論述
Can face the phenomenon of democracy
能面對民主這個現象
It actually has a contradiction
它其實有一個矛盾性
This contradiction means that
這個矛盾性就是說
On the one hand, it is historically
它一方面是歷史上來講是
very later
很後來
Is of course it when starting with historical experience
就是當然它當開始有歷史的經驗
in the western world
在西方的世界
is very much an afterthought
是非常後來產生的東西
But a value of our current politics
可是我們現在的政治的一個價值
or a moral sub bureau
或者是一個道德的子局
when we ask ourselves
當我們問我們自己
Democracy is not our own true value when
民主是不是我們自己真實的價值的時候
Most people will answer
絕大部分的人都會回答
Yes means that this universality
Yes 也就是說這個普遍性
in many countries
在許許多多的國家當中
Until now
到現在為止
Already compared to the late 1980s
已經比80年代末期
The Disintegration of Socialism in the Early 1990s
90年代初期的社會主義瓦解說
Until now
到現在為止
The degree of support for such a view
這樣的一個觀點的支持度
In fact, it is getting higher and higher
其實是越來越高了
Then I insert a
那麼我這個地方插入一個
Chinese and democratic such a
中國人與民主的這樣的一個
power point means
power point就是說
Democracy is unimaginable
民主這個難以想像
then in the nineteenth century
那麼在十九世紀
When we first started contacting the West
我們剛剛開始跟西方接觸的時候
It is not easy to imagine the meaning of democracy
是不太容易imagined democracy這個意思
So so in the nineteenth century
那麼所以在十九世紀的
In the second half of the night, during the time of Yin and Han
下半夜的殷漢時點當中
This concept was once forced
這個概念曾經被迫
translated into multiplayer
翻譯成多人亂管
A lot of people mess with the tube
很多人亂七八糟的管
Or the petty people take power
或者是小民弄權
There are many other ways
還有許多其他的方法
Then until the beginning of the twentieth century
那麼一直到二十世紀初
in a very short time
在非常短的時間當中
About ten or twenty years
大約十幾二十年當中呢
then he is stabilized
那麼他被穩定化
That is to say, to remove such a
就是說去除掉那樣的一種
judgment of value
價值的判斷
translated into civil affairs
翻譯成民政
or democracy, etc.
或民主之國政等等
Not only that
不僅如此
He is less than twenty years old
他就在不到二十年之間呢
Then in the samurai movement
那麼在武士運動當中
Mr. De
他被標舉為德先生
Of course we are well aware of the history of this
當然我們非常清楚這段的歷史
There are many advanced
在座有很多先進
Also did a lot of research
也做過很精深的研究
The so-called Mr. De
所謂的德先生
Mr. Sai Democracy
賽先生這個Democracy
and Science
和Science
is considered to be one of the rescuers of China
就被認為是解救中國的一個
Bolfamen
博爾法門
i sometimes think
我有時候在想
I have not done research
我並沒有做過研究
Why didn't they talk about freedom and science?
當時為什麼不會講自由跟科學
there must be a special reason for this
這一定有一個特殊的原因
Is there some sense of democracy in
是不是某種民主的意義是在
chance above
機緣上面
on the root
在根源上面
There is some kind of power that touches people's hearts
就有某種觸動人心的力量
Of course we can come back slowly
這個當然我們可以慢慢再來
discuss this matter
討論這件事情
then this is a
那麼這個是一個
A few weeks ago I went to a
前幾個禮拜我去參加一個
I was invited to comment on a
我被邀請去評論一個
A technical article
一個technical的文章
It's not really my specialty
其實不是我的專長
but in this place
但在這個地方呢
it is a survey
它是一個調查
It is a survey of East Asian values
就是東亞價值一個調查
A Thing That Investigates Democratic Values
調查民主價值的一個東西
we invite you to watch this
我們請大家看這個
this problem
這個問題
He said democracy may have its problem
他說 democracy may have its problem
but it is still the best form of government
but it is still the best form of government
This respondent was asked the question
這個受訪者被問這個問題
answer this question
這個問題回答
Yes is 76.18
yes的是76.18
such a number
這樣一個數字
Then such a number
那麼這樣一個數字
Let's look at the support degree
支持度我們看這個整個來講的話
it is almost the highest
它是幾乎是最高
It's the same as this one except
它除了跟這個是一樣之外
Which country did the respondent answer?
那這是哪一個國家的受訪者的回答呢
this is mainland china
這是中國大陸
It is man in China
It is man in China
Well then I'll comment on that article
那麼那我去評論那篇文章
Nothing to do with today's topic
跟今天的主題沒有關係
because for him
因為對他來講
It produces a very interesting puzzle
它產生了一個很有趣的puzzle
because he said
因為他說
Another problem is
另外的問題是
I would prefer live under our system of government
I would prefer live under our system of government
any other than I can think of
any other than I can think of
He replied that freedom is the best system
他回答自由是最好的體制
Then you can live under this system in mainland China
那你可活在中國大陸的這個體制之下
so they empirical people
所以他們 empirical 的人
That is to say, those who make this empirical theory should return
就是說做這個經驗理論的人要回
I want to ask if this is a fake
要問說這是不是做造假的
or he is cheating
或者他是欺騙的
Or he's going to make one of these two numbers
或者他要去把這兩個數字做一個
make a bond
做一個結合
Said he was going to offer an explanation
說他要提出一個解釋
Why do people in mainland China
為什麼中國大陸的民眾
He himself believes that democracy is a
他本身認為民主是一個
best value ratio
最好的價值的比例
so tall but he
這麼高可是他
Basically accept the authoritarian rule of mainland China
基本上接受中國大陸這個威權的統治
That's not one of our topics today
那這不是我們今天的一個議題
All we're going to see is the
我們要看到的只是在
A country like mainland China
中國大陸這樣的一個國家
Then democracy is also a highly supported
那麼民主也是一個高度被支持
recognized one
被認同的一個
one political value
一個政治的一個價值
So
那麼
I will introduce the following Powerpoints to you
以下幾個 Powerpoint 我跟大家介紹
I have one for you
我有給各位一個
the blue version
藍色的那個版本
is one of my speeches online
是我的一個演講的 online
Then you can refer to
那麼大家可以參照一下
that is
就是說
the one that put a backbone of my speech
那個把我的演講的一個骨幹
put it there
放在那個地方
But the main text because
但是主要的文本因為
Because of space
因為篇幅的關係
I still only put it on the Powerpoint side
我還是只有放在 Powerpoint 方面
so
所以
in the following words
在以下來講的話
Then based on an experience in Taiwan
那麼基於台灣的一個經驗
Let me introduce to you
我跟各位介紹一下就是說
How do we view democracy in Taiwan
我們台灣怎麼看民主
So one of the key points of this issue is to say
那麼這個議題的一個重點就是說
Let's go to Taiwan's public discourse
我們去看台灣的公共論述
I'm just very simple
我只是很簡單的
As far as I can remember, I took two paragraphs of text
我印象所及我就取了兩段文字
Then you can see
那麼大家可以看看
Can't see where this text comes from
看不看得出來這文字是從哪裡來的
Then the first paragraph
那麼第一個paragraph
this is a quarter
這是一個quartation
it is a cryptogram
它是一個隱文
He said Taiwan's democracy dilemma was never really implemented
他說台灣的民主困境是從未真正落實
constitutionalism
的憲政主義constitutionalism
This is the spirit of the original text
這是原文的精神
Constitutionalism emphasizes separation of powers and checks and balances
憲政主義強調分權制衡
Advocating the Rule of Law and Defending Basic Human Rights
主張法治與捍衛基本人權
And strict constitutional government must not abuse power
並嚴格憲政政府不得濫用權利
This is the necessary foundation for a good democracy
這是優質民主必要的基礎
However, in the time zone where democracy was in Taiwan
然而在民主在台灣的時間區
biased towards elections
偏重於選舉
The essence of democracy
對於民主的實質內涵
The idea of ​​constitutionalism
憲政主義的理念
not paying enough attention to
未能給予足夠的重視
As a result, except for politicians who violated the law and abused their power
以致除了政治人物違法濫權不外
All walks of life except greed
各界除了惡婪之外
Jin can't make a difference
進不能有所作為
So in modern times this is continuous
那麼近代這是連續的
modern western democracy
近代西方民主
even developed successfully because
甚至得以順利發展是因為
Keep the spirit of constitutionalism first
先守憲政主義的精神
Constitutionalism asserts that everyone has inalienable fundamental rights
憲政主義主張人人擁有不可剝奪的基本權利
Government rights must be limited
政府權利必須受到截至
the constitution of the law makes everyone equal
法律制憲人人平等
follow the law
一切措施以法而行
The administrative system is strictly neutral
行政體系嚴守中立
These are the basic principles of a democracy against
這些基本原則是一個民主國家對抗
Despotism or populism please note this opposition
專制暴政或民粹主義請注意這個對立
we'll talk about that later
我們等一下會談到這個問題
The key is that this is what we pursue for high-quality democracy
關鍵所在這也是我們追求優質民主的
do guarantee
確實保證
So he went on to say that after he came to power
那麼他繼續講就是說當執政之後呢
All efforts to implement the core value of democracy are
一切努力落實民主的核心價值是
Constitutionalism has become the consensus of ruling and opposition parties
憲政主義成為朝野政黨的共識
We look forward to the DPP, of course this is President Ma
我們期待民進黨當然這是這個馬總統
A white arm of this constitutional reform at the time of the first election
第一次選舉的時候的這個憲政改革的一個白臂
still available online
網路上還是拿得到
Then we expect the DPP not to be subject to
那麼我們期待民進黨不要受制於
Taiwanese democracy thereby abandoning their commitment to
台灣民主主義從而放棄他們對於
Surveillance due to constitutional democracy
憲政民主應有的監視
We also advocate the addition of constitutionalism, nationalism, etc.
我們也主張加上憲政主義國民主義等等
This is a view of democracy
這是一種對於民主的一個看法
Well, this view is of course what we generally call
那這個看法當然是我們一般叫做
constitutional democracy
憲政民主
Then sometimes his value is Liber
那麼有的時候他的價值是Liber
we are called
我們叫做
Liber democracy is the constitutionalism of this democracy
Liber democracy是這個民主的憲政主義
But Taiwan has other
但是台灣有其他的
There is another concept of democracy
有另外一種民主的一個概念
the concept it says so
這個概念它這麼說的
building the nation
就是建構國民
It advocates the construction of national sovereignty
它主張建構國民主權
Principles of National sovereignty
National sovereignty的原則
Create a modern constitutional state
建立現代立憲國家
Do not touch the principle of national sovereignty
莫不接觸國民主權原則
emphasize some governance
強調一些施政
between public opinion as a rule
介於以民意為一規
We recommend strengthening direct civil rights
我們建議強化直接民權
establish the principle of national sovereignty
確立國民主權的原則
Let the people know about the law and the affairs of the country
讓人民對法律與全國性的事務
criminal
有刑事
create referendum
創制 復絕之權
It's ready now
現在已經可以了
then it goes on
那麼它繼續講
or another paragraph
或者說是另外一段
citizen hair will be 22 million
公民頭髮將是兩千兩百萬
The people of Taiwan use it to fight against
台灣人民用來對抗
Chinese regime on the other side
對岸中國政權
The most powerful force to annex Taiwan
併吞台灣的最有力
also the last weapon
也最後的武器
even say
甚至說
Even if the citizen's hair is Taiwan
甚至如果說公民頭髮是台灣
The Last Trump Card of People's Governance
人民治保的最後一張王牌
The last line of defense is not an exaggeration
最後一條防線也不為過
then this is in
那麼這個是在
Ah Bian's constitutional policy white skin negligence
阿扁的憲政政策白皮疏失
before the first administration
第一次執政之前
That is, it was proposed in the second millennium AD
也就是公元兩千年所提出來的
These two are very simple
這兩個很簡單的
A discussion in a public forum
公共論壇當中的一個論述
Then their writers are scholars
那麼他們的撰寫者都是學者
I think so but he lays it out nicely
我想那麼但是呢他很好的鋪陳出來
That is to say, even in a place like Taiwan
就是說即使在台灣這樣的一個
in a democratic society
民主的社會當中
our value to democracy
我們對於民主的價值
concept of democracy
對於民主的概念
In fact, there is still a different understanding
其實還是有不同的一個理解的
one way
一個方式的
So are we going to say
所以我們是不是要說
Democracy is an inherently contestable concept
民主上是一個本質上可以爭議的概念
so-called inherently contestable concepts
所謂的本質上可以爭議的概念
a concept in political philosophy
是政治哲學當中一個概念
Called Essentially Contested Concept
叫做Essentially Contested Concept
For example, some concepts
比如說有一些概念來講的話
it's so controversial in itself
它本身的爭議性如此之大
So it is never possible to achieve a
所以永遠不可能對它達到一個
a precise definition
精確的一個定義
which itself defines A must have another definition
它本身定義A一定有另外一個定義
The definition opposed to it yields
跟它對立的定義產生
so we call it an essentially contestable concept
所以我們叫它本質上可以爭議的概念
Then let's look at the previous two videos
那我們看前面兩段影文當中
constitutionalism versus national sovereignty
憲政主義 versus 國民主權
Then populism should be reversed
那麼民粹主義這應該倒過來
fundamental rights versus populism
基本權利 versus 民粹主義
In fact, in the system of different political theories
其實在不同的政治理論的系統當中
can be an important element of democratic political theory
都可以是民主政治理論的重要的元素
But when it is placed in a different context
可是呢當它放在不同的脈絡當中
when it is combined with each other
當它互相結合之後呢
it produces a different context
它產生不一樣的一個語境
Then it will also produce different
那麼它也會產生不一樣的
A this of public policy
公共政策的一個這個
An account of this orientation, etc.
這個導向的一個論述等等
so in other words
所以換言之
Are these mutual democratic concepts Taiwan's
這些互持的民主概念是不是台灣
unique
才特有的呢
what am i talking about
我要講的是不是
this is a
這個是一個
This is a democratic political
這個是一個在民主政治
or the history of the development of the concept of democracy
或民主概念的發展史當中
is a thing that has always existed
是一直存在的一件事情
So democracy in the history of Western political thought
所以民主在西方政治思想史之中
It is also a concept that is constantly changing
也是一個持續變化的一個概念
But we will slowly see
只不過我們慢慢會看到
During the development of the history of the twentieth century
在二十世紀的歷史的發展當中
its competitor is not democracy
它的競爭者不是民主
please first
請大家先
Let me tell you one clue first.
我先把這個某一個線索先講
That is to say, democracy is often overshadowed by its opponents
就是說民主往往是被它的對立者
Defined by
所界定的
so
所以
The second century to the end when his universal
二世紀到最後面當他的普遍
The so-called universal value is his antithesis
所謂的普遍價值是他的對立者
After its own legitimacy slowly fades away
本身的正當性的慢慢的消退之後
A very unique phenomenon that arises
所產生的一個非常獨特的現象
Will there be other historical forms in the future?
那將來會不會有其他的歷史形態
Can compete with liberal democracy or democracy
能夠跟自由民主或者是民主相抗衡
That's one thing I don't know
那個是不知道的一件事情
but
但是呢
Let's see what we've said so far
我們到現在來看來講的話
is indeed a generation of such a general situation
是的確有這樣的一個普遍性的狀況的一個產生
Then in the following
那麼在以下呢
I will enter into my speech and compare
我就進入到我演講當中比較
part of the academic
就是學術性的一個部分就是說
I will go with you as much as possible
我跟各位去盡可能的
in an understandable way
用一個可以理解的方式來
Do an Intellectual History Review
做一個思想史的回顧
It is a review of the history of the idea of ​​democracy
就是這個民主觀念思想史的一個回顧
Then in all the development of political values
那麼在所有的政治價值的發展當中
Democracy is characterized by a second coming
民主的特點是一種再度的降臨
is a second coming
就是一個second coming
Why is he a second coming
為什麼他是一個second coming呢
That is to say, the generation of political value
就是說政治的價值的產生
Whether it is the East or the West
不管是東方不管是西方
In fact, generally speaking, it is actually a specific struggle
其實它一般來講都是在實際上具體的鬥爭
or class conflict
或者是階級的衝突
or one of various
或者是各種各樣的一個
slowly emerged from a de facto political initiative
一個實際上政治的倡議之中慢慢產生
Let's go for an example
我們去對例子來講
the concept of country
國家這個概念
The concept of the state itself is
國家這個概念它本身在
In fact in the English language
實際上在英文的語言當中
used for the first time in our present sense
第一次被用在我們現在意義底下的
When the country is uncertain
國家這個不定下來的時候
Almost at Hobbs' legislator talk
差不多是在霍布斯的立委談
That is, 1650
也就是1650年
Before 1650 there was of course the word State
在1650年之前當然有State這個字
But that State it represents some status
可是那個State它表示的是一些status
is its state
就是它的狀態
Or it will become our current concept of State
或者是它會變成我們現在State的概念
Because it has a meaning of Political status
是因為它有一個Political status的一個意思
that is to say its political status
就是說它的政治的狀態
For example, the political state of a monarch
比如說一個君主的政治的狀態
Then these are more vague
那麼這些比較模糊的一些
daily life terms
日常生活的用語
With this political struggle
隨著這個政治的一個鬥爭
Then during the English Civil War
那麼當時在英國內戰時期
with this aristocracy
跟這個貴族派
Plus one of this sect of various religions
還加上這個各種宗教的教派的一個
In fierce confrontation?
激烈的對抗當中呢
or not hoping to find
或不是希望找到
we two see or not
我們兩個看到或不是
find a higher point
找到一個更高的一個點
what about this time
這個時候呢
The concept of country has been settled
國家這個概念呢被定下來
So what's the difference between him and democracy?
那麼他跟民主比起來有什麼差別呢
Before the concept of the country was settled
在國家這個概念被定下來之前呢
The concept of country is not yet the concept of country
國家這個概念還不是國家這個概念
That is to say, when we use the word State in English,
就是說當我們用英文使用State這個字的時候
The one that pops up in our heads
我們的腦袋當中所浮現的那個
associated, that, that, that, that, that semantic
associated那個那個那個那個語意呢
no country as we speak
沒有我們現在所講的國家
For example, let's talk about the Republic of China
比如說我們講說中華民國
or thinking about the republic of america
或者是想著美利堅共和國
We thought of this certain country
我們想到了這個確定的一個國家
But the concept of democracy is different
可是民主的概念是不一樣
the concept of democracy
民主這個概念
it self in greek city-state
它本身在希臘城邦
In the first Greek city-states
在第一次希臘城邦當中呢
Once a Democracy Experience Is Determined
就有一次確定了一個民主的經驗
So the political value of democracy
所以民主的這個政治的價值
is a bit like China
是有點像中國
I'm making an assumption
我是做一個假設
Forgive my material if there are historians here
在座有歷史學家就原諒我的物質
For example feudal
比如說封建
or Jing Tian
或者是景田
This concept existed 2000 years ago
這個概念是在2000年前曾經存在過的
So
那麼
so it existed as a concept
所以它存在過的一個概念
It was in the 18th century or after the 17th and 8th centuries
它在18世紀或者17、8世紀以後
it re-emerge
它再re-emerge
it slowly reappears
它再慢慢的再浮現出來
And after two or three centuries of development
並且經過兩三世紀的發展
Obtain an overwhelming advantage at the end of the 24th century
在24世紀末取得壓倒性的一個優勢
So the fact of its coming again
所以它的這個再度的降臨這個事實
Not exactly the same as other political concepts
跟其他的政治的概念並不完全一樣
at least in my understanding
至少在我的理解當中不一樣
I hope to be able to tell the difference in a very specific way.
我希望能夠很具體的講出這個差別性
so
所以
But the story of democracy
但是民主的這個故事
how to tell this story
如何來說這個故事
That is to say, democracy started from the city-states of Greece 2,000 years ago
就是說民主從2000年前的希臘的城邦
to modern democracies
到現代的民主國家
or among countries
或者在國家當中
we become a democratic country
我們變成一個民主的國家
or a democratic society
或者是民主的社會
Is this story a historical teleology?
這個故事它是一個歷史的目的論嗎
it's like i'm going to go back and see
它是像我要再去回去看
Fukuyama said like that
福山那樣子說
OK let's put this human
OK 我們把這個人類
a history of us
一個歷史我們
In pursuit of our autonomy
在追求我們追求自主性
We pursue this ego governing ourselves and so on
我們追求這個自我管理自己等等
Then such a kind is regarded as a
那這樣的一種當作是一個
as one of our most important
當作是一個我們最重要的一個
Is it to discuss a kind of dignity of a person?
一個人的一種一種尊嚴之所在來論述嗎
Or are we going to use some social
還是我們要去用一些社會
What about a theory of the evolution of value?
價值的演化的一個理論來加以說明呢
I think it is in our present age
我認為是在我們現在這個時代來講
It's probably not easy to say such a thing
大概已經不容易講這樣的話
I think democracy is a non-intended process
我認為民主是一個non-intended process
it is an unintended one
它是一個非意圖的一個
It is an unintentional process
它是一個非意圖的一個過程
as a researcher of intellectual history
作為一個思想史的研究者
I do not believe in a teleology of history
我不相信歷史的一個目的論
I believe in history
我相信的是在歷史
But what I believe is that in the course of history
但是我相信的是在歷史的過程當中
Historical agency
Historical agency
the actors of history themselves
就是歷史的行動者本身呢
it will have its ideas
它會有它的觀念
Its perceptions can have an impact on its actions
它的觀念會對它的行動有影響
Of course this effect we cannot say is a
當然這影響我們不能說是一個
a british influence
英國的一個影響
it is complicated
它是複雜的
For example, how do I understand democracy
比如說我怎麼理解民主
Democracy as I understand it and democracy as you understand it
我的理解的民主跟你的理解的民主
If we are not the same, we will conflict
不一樣我們就會衝突
but no matter what
可是不管怎麼樣
I
我
Our actions are consistent with our commitment to democracy
我們的行動是跟我們對於民主
or other values ​​of this concept are related
或者其他的價值的這個概念是有關係的
So what about such a process?
那麼這樣的一個過程呢
it has several important features
它有幾個重要的特徵
I have translated it into Chinese in my Hand out
我在我的Hand out裡面是有把它翻譯成中文的
So I express it in English here
那麼我在這個地方特意用英文來表達
First
第一個
Democracy is a Herman-Newtics
Democracy是一個Herman-Newtics
This is probably a rather strange statement.
這個大概是一個比較奇怪的一個說法
I had a discussion with a historian a few days ago
我前幾天還跟一位歷史學者做一個討論
That is to say, history is a whole world
就是說歷史是一個全世界
sorry
對不起
Democracy, the specificity of the presence of democracy that I mentioned earlier
民主我前面所講的民主的在臨的這個特殊性
It's an interesting interpretation of an
它是一個很有趣的一個詮釋的一個
it has a feature that we call hermeneutics
它有一個我們叫做詮釋學的一個特徵
Why do we say it has a hermeneutic character?
為什麼我們說它有一個詮釋學的特徵呢
Because it has a Classical Text
因為它有一個Classical Text
it has a classical tradition
它有一個古典的傳統
classical experience
古典的經驗
The main thing is the politics of Yaris Dorda
主要的就是Yaris Dorda的政治學
There is this classical political philosophy
有這個古典的政治哲學
For Greek democracy at the time
對於當時希臘的民主
and various other monarchies
以及其他的各種君主政治
the concept of the monarch
就是君主的概念
concept of aristocracy concept of aristocracy
貴族的概念 貴族統治的概念
and the concept of democracy
以及民主的概念呢
It has a very complete analysis
它有一個非常完備的一個分析
So it has a text in that place
所以它是有一個text在那個地方的
In ancient democracy, there was a text in that place
古代的民主是有一個text在那個地方的
But it has a contemporary
但是呢 它有一個當代的
A horizon of historical actors
歷史行動者的一個horizon
horizon we know it is a concept of the whole world
horizon我們知道它是一個全世界的一個概念
That's when I'm learning about something
就是我現在在了解一件事情的時候
an agent an actor
一個agent 一個行動者
either an interpreter or a reader
或者是一個詮釋者 或者一個讀者
I probably I didn't read this kalama bless bro before
我可能 我在沒有讀這個卡拉馬祝福兄弟之前
I may have some vague idea of ​​the literature of the book
我可能對於書的文學有某種模糊的概念
one thing i want to know
我希望去了解的一個東西
Well, but my understanding is actually
那麼 但是我的了解要實際上
I have read this novel very thoroughly
我非常透徹地看過這個小說
To various this inside
對裡面的各種各樣的這個
A very complex science of a character
很複雜的一個人物的科化
and its dialogue
以及它的對話
Grand Inquisitor etc.
大宗教審判官等等
after i understand
我有了解之後
I can come out and say how I probably understand this book
我才能出來說我大概怎麼去理解這本書
So is a horizon in this place
所以 是一個horizon在這個地方
So this democracy as an interpretation of an experience
所以呢 這個民主做為一種詮釋的一個經驗
this is thinking
這是在思想的
The level of not wanting is not at the level of reality
不想的層次不是在現實的層次
The level of reality certainly has class interests
現實的層次當然有階級的利益
Then the material struggle and so on
那麼物質的鬥爭等等
this undeniable
這個不否認的
I'm not saying that people are only determined by their ideas
我不是說人只是被他的idea決定的
But the idea exists in this place
但是idea是存在在這個地方
Then the idea of ​​democracy
那這個democracy的idea
Its special place is that
它特別的地方就在於
it has a classical text
它有一個classical text
there is a classical text in that place
有一個古典的文本在那個地方
as a reference
當作是reference
But an interesting aspect of the nation lies in this place
但是民族的一個有趣的地方就在這個地方
It is not like Chinese Jingtian or feudal
它沒有像中國的景田或者是封建
we say we are in the modern world
我們說我們在現代的世界
To put such a system into our modern society
要把這樣的一個制度放到我們現代的社會當中
that often has a devastating consequence
那往往造成的是一個毀滅性的後果
Did democracy have any consequences?
那民主有沒有造成的後果
Democracy in the Western world
民主在西方的世界當中
also caused great political turmoil
也造成了很大的政治動盪
This several revolutions
這個好幾次的大革命
But it's another interesting one
但是它是另外一種很有趣的一個
a state of change
變化的一個樣態
or a changing look
或者一個變化的一個樣子
We call it recontactualization
我們叫做recontactualization
That is to say, democracy itself in the classical period
就是说民主本身在古典时期
as an expression of direct democracy
他作为一种直接民主的一个表述的方式
After he arrived in modern times he was contactualized again
他到了现代之后他重新被contactualized
His value is re-converted
他的价值重新被转换
He transforms into something different than he was
他转换成跟他原来不一样的东西
so what
那么所以呢
The last point is the change of this value of democracy
最后一点就是民主的这个价值的变化
It is an innovative transformational idea
它是一个innovative transformational ideas
That is to say, it is a kind of political value
就是说它是一个对政治价值的一种
mine new a way of changing
矿新的一种改变的一个方式
So this process of change in democracy
所以民主的这个这样的一个改变的过程
let me emphasize again
我再强调一下
there is no one great
是没有某一个伟大的
great philosopher or great legislator
伟大的哲学家或伟大的立法者
Said that democracy should be like this in modern times
说民主应该是现代这个样子
It's not the ancient one, it didn't exist
不是古代那个是没有的
it is in the process
它是在这个过程当中
in generations
在一代又一代的
thinkers in the west
在西方的思想家
and when it came to the east
以及当它到了东方来之后
Thinkers in the East
在东方的思想家
or among historical actors
或者是历史行动的者当中
slowly forming a
慢慢去形成的一个
what we are now
我们现在的一个样貌
Then, in retrospect of the history of thought
那么思想史的回顾来讲
here only know
这边只知道
just a simple one
只是簡單的大概先有一個
orange this place
orange這個地方
That is to say, if we look at the history of Western thought
就是說我們看西方的思想史來講的話
it has a classical democracy
它有一個古典的民主
This is what we generally call direct democracy.
就是我們一般講的直接的民主
that's done in greek sorry
那是以希臘做 對不起
greek city-state
希臘城邦
Especially the city-state of Athens as a model
特別是雅典城邦作為一個範本
Then it has the National Assembly and the People's Court
那麼它有國民大會 有人民法庭
Almost always by lottery
幾乎都是用抽籤的方式
I'm sorry, the National Assembly and the People's Court
對不起 國民大會跟人民法庭
The National Assembly is open to all citizens
國民大會是所有的公民都可以參加的
Then the people's court is very large
那麼人民法庭呢是很大的規模
is a lottery, almost all Greek institutions
是抽籤 幾乎所有希臘的制度
Except for the most important military leaders
除了最重要的軍事的領袖
and financial officials
以及財務的官員之外
all by lottery
都是用抽籤的
Lottery is a mechanism of democracy
抽籤是一個民主的一個機制
then other
那麼其他的
Like the big general I just mentioned
像我剛講的這個大的將軍
or finance officials they use elections
或者是財務官員他們是用選舉
Elections for Greek Democratic Theory
選舉對於希臘的民主理論來講
It's a mechanism for an aristocrat
它是一個貴族的一個機制
It is completely different from what we think now
它跟我們現在的想法是完全不一樣
It's an interesting change in a democracy
這是一個民主很有趣的一個變化
in modern democracy
在現代的民主當中
I differentiate it into two
我把它區分成兩種
That's just a temporary distinction
那这只是暂时一个区分
Everyone probably knows
大家大概知道就好
A Democracy I Call Substantive
一种我叫做实质的民主
This substantive democracy focuses on
这个实质的民主注重的是
substantial democracy
substantial democracy
It focuses on the concept of democracy or the people
它集中在民主或者是人民的概念
Then as a substantive concept
那么作为一个实体性的概念
it is based on the will
它是以意志作为基础
it strives for equality
它追求平等
Equality is always at the heart of democracy
平等永远是民主的核心的
most important value
最重要的一个价值
Of course now we
当然在我们现在
Especially the current society in Taiwan
特别是当前的台湾的社会
everyone is talking about it
大家都在谈这个问题
or the identity of ruler and ruled
或者是统治者与被统治者的同一性
This is a more philosophical expression
这个是比较哲学的表达
identity
identity
which means I don't want to have one
就是说我不要有一个
Perpetual existence also with a group of my comrades
永久存在亦与我的一个同志的团体
king or lord
君主或者是贵主
That's what a comrade looks like
它就是这样一个同志的样态
what democracy imagines is
民主所想象的是
No one is gay with anyone other than us
没有一个亦与我们之外的一个同志者
it must be in
它必须是在
in a process within ourselves
内在于我们的自己的一个过程当中
in the process of democracy
民主的过程当中
in the political process
政治的过程当中
Another concept of democracy is
另外一种民主的概念是
procedural procedure
程序性的 procedure
it is free
它是自由
We sometimes call it Liberal Democracy
我们有时候叫自由民主
or constitutional democracy
或者是宪政民主
Constitutionalism is well expressed
宪政很好的表达出
this
這個
the meaning of procedure
procedure的意思
that speaks freely
那自由來講的話
is compatible with the constitution
是跟憲政搭配的
some concepts of liberty we say libertarianism
我們說自由主義的一些自由的概念
I'll talk about that later
我等一下會稍微談到
What about procedural concepts?
那作為程序性的概念呢
it is rational
它是以理性
in front of will
前面是以意志
these are two different things
這是兩個不一樣的東西
then it pursues a process of rational deliberation
那麼它追求某一種合理審議的過程
and then reach a consensus
然後能達到一個共識
these are two different
這是兩種不同的
modern concept of democracy
現代的民主的概念
What about classical democracy?
跟古典的民主呢
is intentional
是有意的
So
那麼
Let me briefly introduce
我先簡單的介紹一下
The theory of democracy in this classical period
這個古典時期的這個民主的理論
that same
那同樣的
In our look at Greek political theory
在我們看希臘的政治理論
words in greek political thought
希臘的政治思想當中的話
We can distinguish that
我們可以區分就是說
how democratic democratic actors understand themselves
民主的民主民主的行動者如何自我理解
That is to say your self understanding
就是說你的self understanding
your self-knowledge
你的自我了解
and what do we do with the concept of democracy
以及我們怎麼樣對於民主這個概念做
what we call scientific analysis
我們叫做科學的分析
or academic analysis
或者是學術的分析
that democratic self-understanding
那民主的自我理解
One of the best in Greece
在希臘是在最好的一個
That is, Perecholus' national business talk is Funeral Oration
就是Perecholus的國商講是Funeral Oration
It is included in the rest of the physical division
它是被收錄在休息體體師的
Among Borobinissa warriors
博羅賓尼薩戰士當中
Then one of its contexts is a time in Greece
那它的一個脈絡是在希臘的一次
during the battle
戰役當中呢
Then there is the messenger of the warrior
那麼有戰士的使者
Then this Perecholus was
那麼這個Perecholus是當時
leader of the greek nation
希臘民族的領袖
So according to the custom at that time
所以按照當時的習慣
This is where these fallen soldiers are buried
就在埋葬這些這個陣亡將士的這個
During this funeral
這個喪禮當中發
that is to say, made a
就是說做了一個
gave a very famous speech
做了一個非常有名的演講
what this speech is about
這個演講來講的話
it's going to inspire
它要去激勵人心
so it's against this family widow
所以它對著這個家人寡婦
What about these relatives of the soldier?
戰士的這個戰士的這些親屬呢
to tell a story about the Greek nation
去講了一個對於希臘民族
worthy of their relatives
值得他們的這個親人呢
For such a circle
為之圈圈區的這樣一個
a very famous lecturer
非常有名的一個講師
Of course everyone is interested
那當然大家有興趣
you can find it for reference
就可以找出來參考
the Chinese translation
那中文的翻譯本
In the Anthology of many nations
在很多民族的Anthology都有
In ethnic Text
在民族的Text
Then one of its main
那麼它中間的一個主要的
actually
實際上的
He said our system is called a democracy
說法他說我們的制度之所以被稱為民主制
because the city-state has a majority of people
是因為城邦是有大多數人
rather than being managed by a handful of people
而不是有極少數人加以管理的
We see that when the law resolves its own disputes
我們看到法律在解決自身爭端的時候
Provides equal justice for all
為所有的人都提供了平等的公正
equality and justice
equality and justice
then in public life
那麼在公共生活當中
priority for public office
優先承擔公職
Consider a person's talents
考慮的是一個人的才能
rather than his social status
而不是他的社會地位
or what class does he belong to etc.
或者他屬於哪個階級等等
Of course, there is a very small paragraph in the middle of the word.
那當然這字中間非常小的一段
Well but we see a
那麼但是我們中間看到一個
The key concept is
關鍵的概念就是
Democracy is the rule of the majority
就是民主他是大多數人的統治
So in the future development
那麼所以在往後的發展當中
For the concept of the majority
對於這個多數這個概念
What priority does he have to climb this
他到底具有什麼優先性可以climb這個
he has the legitimacy to rule
他具有統治的正當性
This is a key question
這是一個關鍵上的一個問題
So let's look at this now
那麼我們現在看這個
What about Aristotle's theory?
亞里斯多德的理論呢
It is different from the previous rest geography
跟前面的休息地理是不一樣的
He is an analysis of what we now call science
他是一個我們現在叫做科學的分析
Analysis of Political Science
政治科學的分析
Of course we don't call him political science now
當然我們現在不會叫他政治科學
Analysis of Political Philosophy or Analysis of Political Theory
政治哲學的分析或政治理論的分析
it is the experience
它是把經驗
it when aristotle collected
它當亞利斯多德收集了
Constitutions of three or four hundred small Greek city-states
三四百個希臘小城邦的憲法
Then it analyzes the logic of democracy
然後它分析民主的邏輯
it analyzes the logic of nobility
它分析貴族的邏輯
It divides Greek society without a monarchical element
它分希臘社會沒有君主要素
This will be mentioned later
這個等下會提到
so what
所以呢
It proposes a very complete text
它提出來一個非常完整的一個text
For Westerners, this structure
那這個架構對於西方人的
understanding at that time
當時的了解
and for us modern times in the West
以及對於我們現代在西方
Democracy regenerates an influence
民主重新產生一個影響力
It acts as a key influence
它扮演了一個關鍵性的影響力
let's see what it says
我們看看它是怎麼說的
Then it appears to be a
那麼它表面上看來是一個
very simple classification
非常簡單的一個分類
then it scales with the number of rulers
那麼它按照統治者的數量
I think many of the guests may know
我想有不少來賓可能知道
It uses a single individual minority and majority
它用單一的個人少數人跟多數人
This is a quantitative standard
這個是一個數量的標準
Then it divides into its rulers
然後它分成它統治者呢
Is it based on common interests
是不是依據共同利益
or it follows the ruler's self-interest
或者它按照統治者的私利
Divided into government and debate
分成政體跟辯體
It is a correct system and a
就是一個正確的體制跟一個
perverted is a formal body of corruption
perverted 就是腐化的一個正體
Then he divides into this single body which is the monarch body
那麼他分成這個單一的正體是君主正體
good formal
好正體
A good orthodox is a monarch orthodox
好的正體是君主正體
aristocratic and republican
貴族正體跟共和正體
I'll talk later
這等下我再講
So the body of the defense is the founder is terranine
那麼辯體的呢是建主是terranine
This is sometimes translated into a tyrant
這個是有的時候翻成暴君
But terranine is a builder
可是terranine是一個建主
It is a translation that is more neutral than ours
是一個比較我們一般比較中性的一個翻譯
But everyone knows that it is terranine
但是大家知道是terranine就好了
oligarch is arigaki
寡頭是arigaki
or arigaki
或是arigaki
But what we saw was interesting in this place
可是我們看到的有趣的是在這個地方
The main body of democracy is placed in the main body of debate
民主正體是放在辯體的正體當中
that is to say
那麼也就是說
His logical circularity does not mean that the monarchy, aristocracy, and democracy
他的這個邏輯上的周圓性並不是把君主貴族民主
Founder or tyrant oligarch
建主或者暴君寡頭
or something to put here
或者是什麼東西放在這裡
There is also Aristotle's political theory
也有阿里斯多德他的這個政治的理論
Political Theories Influencing the West for Two Thousand Years
影響到西方兩千年的政治理論
We say he might have some vibe of some democracy
我們說他可能有一些民主的一些vibe
Well, but you go to see Aristotle
那麼但是你去看亞里斯多德
His articles are not many
他的篇章其實並不多的
for every regime
他對於每一個政體
his non-existent monarchy for greece
他對於希臘所不存在的君主政體
he clearly pointed out
他很明確的指出來
The virtue of his ruler is an extraordinary virtue
他統治者的德性是一個extraordinary virtue
use one of us
用一個我們
A metaphor well understood by the Chinese
中國人比較了解的一個比喻
For example, Dahe Zhishui
比如說大與治水
Yamato was three generations before
大與之前是三代
Great and before is kindness
大與之前是善讓
But Da Yu's virtue is so high
可是大與的德性如此之高
his achievement is so big
他的achievement如此之大
make the people willing to regard him as a monarch
使得人民願意奉他為君主
this is a monarchy
這個是君主政體
That is to say, the monarch's morality
也就是說君主他的道德上
basis of legitimacy
或者正當性的基礎
is a single individual
是單一的個人
a very special virtue
非常特殊的一個德性
the aristocracy is
那貴族政體就是
The concept of virtual virtue
virtual的德性這個概念
then democracies
那麼民主政體
We see that his actual analysis is
我們看他實際上的分析是
equal to the liberty
equal to the liberty
The two principles are equality and liberty
兩個原則就是平等以及自由
So Aristotle for
所以亞里斯多德對於
Analysis of Democracy
對於民主的分析
It's not as simple as we are now
並沒有像現在我們單純的
look
看
You are biased towards him
你你前而对他是有Bias
Of course there is a little bias
当然是有一点Bias
Aristotle thought
那亚利斯多德认为
What does he think is the best form of government?
他认为最好的一个政体是什么东西呢
It's this kind of regime mixed with this
是这个跟这个混合起来的这种政体
so
所以
What about the rule of many people in the regime?
政体的多人的统治呢
He's called a republic called a Polity
他叫做共和政体叫做Polity
The concept of Polity is a mixture of oligarchy and democracy
Polity这个概念是寡头跟民主的混合
He believes that oligarchy and democracy are the same
他认为寡头的政体跟民主的政体就是
At that time the Greek two class struggle
当时希腊两个阶级斗争
The two most powerful classes in conflict
冲突的最厉害的两个阶级
a class of nobility
一个是贵族的阶级
The worse state is the oligarch
比较不好的状态就是寡头
Then the other is the democratic majority
那么另外一个就是民主的多数
Bad state is democracy
不好的状态就是民主
what about these two
这两个呢
It's all over
都是过
This fate means the middle of the mean
这个命的意思就是中庸中间
Aristotle's philosophy
亚利斯多德的这个哲学
It's a bit like the Confucian philosophy in China.
有点像中国的这个儒家的哲学要讲
The golden mean
中庸之道
So these two are Access
那么这两个呢都是Access
The pursuit of wealth or virtue is not considered
本来追求财富或者是德性不算
pursuit of wealth or virtue
追求财富或者是德性
he both he all he is a good thing
他都 他都 他都是一件好事
Equality and liberty are also a good thing
平等跟自由也是一件好事
But what?
可是呢
they chased
他們追著過頭
After it's over, it becomes over
過頭之後呢就變成過了
After that, we need to put two
過了之後呢就要把兩個
through some mechanism
通過一些機制
This is the city-state
就是城邦的這個
What about these mechanisms?
把這些機制呢
mix it up
把它混合起來
then become the so-called republic
那麼成為所謂的共和政治
What about the concept of Aristotle?
亞里斯多德這個概念呢
It affected this across the West
它影響了整個西方的這個
a political thought
政治的一個思想
But what I just said
但是呢就我剛剛講的
it actually to some extent
它其實在某個程度上
There is a stigmatization of democracy
有一種民主的污名化
But this stigmatization
但是這個污名化
Stigmatization in Chinese
污名化用中文來講
pretty ugly
蠻難聽的
stigma
stigma
That is to say, it actually
就是說它其實把它
missing a label in that place
缺了一個標籤在那個地方
But is there a theoretical reason for this label?
但這個標籤有沒有理論的理由呢
Let's see there's actually a reason
我們看看其實有一點理由的
it says so
它這麼說
it says democracy
它說democracy呢
是the rule of many
是the rule of many
with a view to the advantage of many only
with a view to the advantage of many only
That is to say, according to its political system and defense system
就是說按照它政體跟辯體的
if this category
這個分類的話
What about democratic rule?
那麼民主的統治呢
is majority rule
是多數的統治
But it only takes care of its own interests
但是它只兼顧到自己的利益
Then we will still ask
那我們現在還會問
this right
這個對
our democratic majority vote
我們民主多數的投票
Then cast out one I am now
然後投出來一個我現在
The political party you are supporting is a democratic process
在支持的政黨就是民主的過程嘛
Aristotle didn't see it that way
亞里斯多德不是這樣看
Well, but we don't care about this for now
那麼但是這個我們暫時不管
focus on this place
重點在這個地方
Many is in Aristotle's system
Many在亞里斯多德的這個系統當中呢
it's just a part
它只是一個部分
So democracy is either aristocrats or monarchs
所以民主或者是貴族或者是君主
it's all just a part
它都只是一個part
This part allows democracy itself to have an advantage in numbers
這個part就讓民主本身原來數量上的優勢說
we are the majority
我們是多數的
or most of us
或是我們絕大多數的人
we should have the legitimacy to rule
我們應該具有統治的正當性的
What about the legitimacy?
這個正當性呢
it wipes it out
它把它給消滅
or weaken it
或是把它削弱
it's about you
它講的說你再怎麼樣
you are all part of the regime
你都是part of the regime
You are just a part of the cost
你只是這個成本當中的一個部分而已
you as a part
你作為一個部分
You said you were going to be the ruler with a few nobles
你說你要作為統治者跟少數的貴族
Suppose he is virtuous
假設是他有德性的
This place is where we see the difference between ancient times and modern times
這個地方就是我們看到古代跟現代的一個分野
According to Aristotle, a minority elite
在亞里斯多德來講一個少數的精英分子
They are of higher virtue
他們是有比較高的德性
or better
或者是有比較好的
We must have the ability to rule
我們要有一個統治的能力
it constitutes a claim to a justifiable dominion
它構成一個具有正當性的統治的一個宣稱
But in our modern
可是在我們現代
we do not accept the concept
我們不接受這個概念
We'll see why later
我們等下會看到為什麼
So
那麼
one
一個
Another important change
再有一個重要的一個變化
He said this Many is always poor
他說這個Many永遠是poor
that is
就是說
it has an iron law
它有一個鐵律
Have you ever seen anything in this world
你有沒有看到任何這個世界當中
in any society
任何的社會當中
rich people are few
有錢人是少數
the poor are the majority
窮人是多數
He said there is no such society
他說不存在在這樣的社會
So Many will always be poor or common people
所以Many永遠是窮者或者是平民
so we put him
所以我們把他
this is his words
這個是他的話
we replace him
我們把他替代下來
So his labeling of democracy
所以他對於民主的一個標籤化
that is
就是說
Democracy is the rule of the poor
Democracy is the rule of the poor
with a view to the delineable poor home
with a view to the delineable poor home
So
那麼
so
所以
This is the whole of the West until modern times
這個是整個西方一直到近代以前
for democracy
對於民主
after the pro-democracy demonstrations
當民主示威之後
what people remember
人們所記住的
Probably just a Greek city-state over 200 years old
大概只是希臘城邦200多年的歷史
very confusing
非常的混亂
call back and forth
打來打去朝來朝去
So
那麼
Even now we look at the history of Western political thought
甚至我們現在看西洋政治思想史
In fact, there is a very interesting example that says
其實有一個很有趣的一個例子就是說
You go to see Greek democracy
你去看希臘的民主
You can't see democracy itself
你不太看得到民主自己
Except the rest body is what I just cited
除了休息機體是我剛剛引的
this fumal ration
這個fumal ration
you don't see a theorist
你看不到一個理論家
For this democracy propose a
對於這個民主提出一個
how about a system
怎麼樣系統的一個
A justification of war promise
戰許式的一個justification
why
為什麼呢
because Greek democracy
因為希臘的民主
Just like our current democracy
就跟我們現在的民主差不多
Most of the action of democracy takes place in that field
大部分民主的行動都在那個場域當中
all at that civic assembly
都在那個公民大會
in the people's assembly
在人民大會當中
one of them trained themselves to speak
他們訓練自己的說話的一個
an ability to stop
休止的一個能力
talking about what we should do now
在說我們現在應該要幹嘛
What attitude should we adopt towards China
我們應該要對中國採取什麼樣的態度
what should we do to america
我們應該對美國怎麼樣
What should we do with American cows
我們應該對美牛怎麼樣
I'm going to convince a
我要去說服一個
sometimes one in ten thousand
有的時候是一萬人的一個
a place for gatherings
聚會的一個場所
this is greek from sophist
這是希臘從sophist開始
That is to say, the self-reproach
就是說這個自責派
training this public one says
訓練這個公共的一個說
A technique for a public speech
公共的一個speech演講的一個技巧
We now see the familiar
我們現在看到大家所熟悉的
This stigma went to one of the Roman era
這個污名化到了羅馬時代的一個
Greek historian called Polybius
希臘的史家叫Polybius
Polybius made a correction
Polybius他就做了一個修正
This revision affected the later Western
這個修正影響了西方的後來的這個
He put the democratic court into the political system
他把民主政庭就放到政體來了
At this time, democracy is in the context of Rome
這個時候民主在羅馬的脈絡當中
So the Romans were basically gay oligarchs
那麼羅馬人基本上還是寡頭同志的
The power of his nobility is still great
他的貴族的力量還是很大的
But the concept of people in Rome
可是羅馬的那個people的概念
is a legal concept
是一個法律上的一個概念
So they themselves for this
所以他們本身對於這個
The Three Elements of Monarchy, Nobility and Democracy
君主貴族跟民主三個元素
It is a more balanced consideration
是做一個比較平衡的一個考慮
So Polybius is here
所以Polybius在這個地方呢
Orthodoxy
把民主政體放到了正體
It is the right system
正就是正確的一個體制
Then variants are no longer democracy.
那麼變體的呢就不再是民主了
He called him coined a word called mob regime
他叫做他創了一個字叫做暴民政體
Then this is more in line with our imagination
那這個比較符合我們的想像
democracy is good
民主是好的嘛
That mutant mob, right?
那個變體的暴民對不對
each has good and each has bad
那每一個都有好的每個都有壞
what about the really good stuff
那真正好的東西呢
Just now Aristotle had only two things mixed
剛才亞里斯多德只有兩個東西混合
that is
就是
The de facto nobles and commoners in Greece at that time
當時希臘實際上的貴族跟平民
Also ample filling for both factions
也是充足的充塗的兩個派系
two classes
兩個階級
What now
現在呢
It creates another new concept that is
它就造成了另外一個新的概念就是
A mixed constitution is three mixed
混合的憲政是三個混合
Of course it's because Rome
那當然也因為羅馬
He himself before becoming a republic
他本身在成為共和之前呢
there is a shift in monarchy
就有君主治的一個移序
So
那麼
re-enter the modern
再進入到現代
Actually I need to go faster
其實我需要快一點
i found out that time is not enough
我發現時間不夠
So
那麼
i want to talk a little bit
我要稍微談一下
That is in Aristotle's concept of politics
那在亞里斯多德這個政治的概念當中
i will call it
我會把它叫做
Xunhua Democracy
它要循化民主
That is to say, democracy is a
就是說民主對它來講是一個
is a difficult one to control
是一個很難控制的一個
a political process
一個政治的一個過程
So it has to cycle
所以它要循化
So the classical theory
所以古典的理論
Its cycle concept is called regimen
它的循化的概念叫做regime
called politics
叫做政治
is pollution
就是pollity
polythea
polytheia
This concept is sometimes used in English translations
這個概念有的時候在英文翻譯本
translate it into constitution
把它翻譯成constitution
not a good translation
不是一個很好的翻譯
Now that the better one is translated into regimen
現在比較好的一本就把它翻譯成regime
Although sometimes in contemporary politics
雖然有的時候在當代的政治裡面
Regime also represents the concept of regime
regime又代表政權什麼這個概念
but we are
但是我們在
I usually translate it into politics
我是一般把它翻譯成政治
for a very specific purpose
就非常特定的一個用意
So Aristotle for politics
那麼亞里斯多德對於政治
He brought it up to say
他提出來就是說
for official position
是對於官職
Especially this authoritative official position
特別是這個具有權威性的官職
an arrangement of a political order
所做的一個政治秩序的一個安排
Then the point is the next decision
那麼重點是下任之決
He said that no matter what type of city-state
他說城邦無論是哪一種類型
His authority must rest with a ruling body
他的權威一定寄託一統治團體
That is to say, in terms of classical theory
就是說古典的理論來講
The very machine world we just talked about
我們剛剛講的那個很機界的一個
Classification that looks very machine-bound
看起來很機界的分類
His focus is on
他的重點是在於
a group capable of forming a mixed rule
能夠形構一個混合的統治的一個團體
So out of six or three of these pure regimes
所以在六種或三種這種純粹的政體當中
He said, for example, that democracy is
他說譬如說民主的就是
Democracy is the authority of the common people
民主政治就是平民擁有權威
An oligarchy is a minority with authority
寡頭政體是有少數人擁有權威
Well but what they hope to do
那麼但是他們希望做到的
this mixed constitution
這個混合的憲政
His purpose is to bring democracy
他的目的是將民主
Democracy into a mechanism for a balance of power
民主納入一個權力平衡的一個機制
is a balance of power
是一個balance of power
So whether it's oligarchs or democracies
那麼無論是寡頭跟民主
In Aristotle there are only two powers
在亞里多德只有兩個力量
or royal aristocrats
或者是王政貴族
It's Malaysia and Astaksi
就是馬來西跟阿斯塔克西
Plus the three forces of democracy
加上民主三個力量
Three groups of Dingli
三組鼎力
This is from the Western period
這個是西方時期的
A heart of an art of classical politics
古典政治的一個藝術的一個核心
The entirety of Western politics predates modern times
整個西方政治在現代之前
It's basically clouded by this analysis
它基本上是被這個分析給籠罩住的
that is to say
那麼也就是說
If you have read Plato's Republic
假如大家有看柏拉圖的Republic
It's Utopia
就是理想國的話
you will see a
你會看到一個
We are called the Guardian Model
我們叫做Guardian Model
that is
就是說
So the concept of politics in the West is the balance of power
所以西方的政治的概念是權力的平衡
It is not an
它並不是一個在柏拉圖所講的
That is to say, politics should have a professional
就是說政治應該有一個專業的
this ruler with true knowledge
這個具有真正知識的統治者
or defenders to rule over us
或衛國者來統治我們
not such a concept
不是這樣的一個概念
when you look at plato
就你看柏拉圖的時候
You'll see another very specific concept
你會看到另一個非常特定的一個概念
But what about that concept?
可是那個概念呢
In the development of the West, it is not the main
在西方的發展當中其實不是主的
The mainstream was developed by Aristotle and Rome
主流是由亞里斯多德跟羅馬所發展出來的
This republic and the concept of mixed constitutionalism
這個共和跟混合憲政的這個概念
So I'm going to move on now to our comparison
那麼我現在就進入到我們比較
actually takes more time
實際上要花比較更多時間的
modern democracy and competition
就是現代的民主跟競爭者
then in my mind
那麼在我的想法當中
or in my interpretation
或在我的詮釋當中
What about modern democracy itself?
現代的民主本身呢
it begets itself because of its competitors
它是因為它的競爭者而產生了自我的
a repositioning
一個重新的一個定位
a new identification
重新的一個認定
So this competitor followed the modern
所以這個競爭者又隨著近代
A development in different phases of this politics
這個政治的不同階段的一個發展
Then the earliest ones are State Building and Nation
那麼最早的是State Building跟Nation
Tell us about nation building and democracy building
對我們講國家的建構跟民主的建構
What about the construction of this country and the construction of democracy?
這個國家的建構跟民主的建構呢
Let the concept of democracy revisit Monarchy and Aristocracy
讓民主這個概念重新對Monarchy跟Aristocracy
These two things launched a new wave of a struggle
這兩個東西展開了新一波的一個鬥爭
It's different from the ancient struggle
跟古代的鬥爭是不一樣
what about after this fight
那麼這個鬥爭之後呢
yes
是
Compared with the later liberalism
比較後來一點的liberalism
That is, we will see constitutionalism versus despotism
就是我們會看到constitutionalism versus despotism
this concept
這個概念
A Concept of Despotism is a Novelty Pro Concept
專制的一個概念是一個新奇臨的概念
Its Aristotelian system does not exist
它的亞里斯多德的系統是不存在的
the word is greek
這個字是希臘文
but it didn't exist
可是它原來不存在
We will see this word later
這個字我們等會再看到
It has an influence on China
它對於中國是有影響的
Because authoritarian politics refers to Chinese style
因為專制政治指的是中國式的
one politics of the monarch
君主的一個政治
That is what Montes said about
那就是孟德士就以下所講的
Then in the second half of the nineteenth century
然後到了十九世紀的下半夜
a contender for the last wave of democracy
最後一波民主的一個競爭者
It is the social revolution
就是social revolution
When it comes to Marx and the socialist revolution
就是到馬克思以及社會主義的革命時候
Generated another wave of democracy versus dictatorship
產生了另外一波democracy versus dictatorship
the concept of dictatorship
就是獨裁的概念
Or later when translated into this
或者是後來當翻譯成這個
dictatorship of the proteria
dictatorship of the proteria
is the proletariat
就是無產階級
officially translated as dictatorship
正式翻譯成專政
But the word dictatorship
可是專政這個字
In fact, it is better translated as dictatorship
其實是翻譯成獨裁比較好
But that topic probably won't be discussed today.
不過這個今天大概是不會討論到那個議題
then i'll go back
那麼我就回到
The first important context is democracy
第一個重要的脈絡就是民主
its first
它的第一種
The first week is related to the modern sovereign state
第一个星期是跟现代的主权国家是有关系的
The concept of sovereignty is very familiar to us
主权概念我们非常熟悉
But the first definition of sovereignty was in
可是主权的第一次的定义是在
not only in the six volumes of treatise on states
不单在邦国论六卷
Six Books on the Commonwealth
Six Books on the Commonwealth
a definition it proposes
它提出来的一个定义
Around 16, 16, 70 years
大概在16、16、70年左右
it says that sovereignty is owned by the political community
它说主权是政治共同体所拥有的
absolute and permanent right
绝对而且永久的权利
Absolute and perpetual
Absolute and perpetual
These two properties
这两个属性
Then this attribute is in addition to absolute and puppetual
那么这个属性除了absolute跟puppetual之外
I just talk to you today
我今天只跟各位谈
It also adds a very important thing to the discussion
它在论述当中还加了一个非常重要的事情
called indivisible
叫做不可分割
Indivisible?
不可分割这个事情呢
Democracy and nobility and monarchy
就让民主跟贵族跟君主
it produced a different one theory one
它产生了一个不同的一个理论的一个
not just theory
不只是理论
that is to say an actual
就是说一个实际上
A change in the arrangement of our political system
我们在政治制度的安排之上的一个变化
It is because sovereignty is indivisible
就是因为主权它是不可以分割的
So it overturns
所以它就推翻了
The classical common
我们前面看到的古典共同
he's a balance of power vs a mixed one
他的一個權力的平衡跟混合的一個
a concept of constitutionalism
憲政的一個概念
That concept is mixing and balancing
那個概念是就是混合跟平衡
Then a topic that gave rise to a whole new theory
那麼產生了一個全新的理論的一個議題
So there can only be three forms of a sovereign state
那麼主權國家呢只能有三種形式
So there are no longer six
所以不再有六種
In terms of HOPS, only monarchy, aristocracy and democracy
用HOPS來講說只有君主貴族以及民主
The so-called tyrant is just you don't like the monarchy
那所謂的暴君只是你不喜歡君主制
The so-called mob is nothing but
所謂的這個暴民只不過是
you
你這個人
That is to say you go to say this person
就是說你去講這個話的人
I don't like democracy
不喜歡民主制而已
say no three things
說沒有三個東西
sorry
對不起
There are no six things, only three things
沒有六個東西只有三個東西
what about this time
那麼這個時候呢
What about monarchy and aristocracy?
君主貴族跟民主呢
they are about to establish
他們就要確立
Who is the sovereign in this struggle?
誰是主權者的這個鬥爭呢
in the age of absolutism
就是在絕對主義時代
the most important one
最重要的一個
a political issue
政治上的一個議題
but this time
但這個時候
yields a classical theory
產生一個在古典理論當中
A problem that doesn't actually arise
其實並不出現的一個問題
people are diverse
人民是雜多的
People, we are now, we have one hundred and fifty or sixty people here
人民我們現在現在我們在座有一百五六十位
Then there are more than 22 million people in Taiwan
那麼全臺灣有兩千兩百多萬
right
對不對
Then among the Greek city-states
那麼在希臘的城邦當中
In his heyday, he had about 50,000 people
全盛時期他大概有五萬多人
but no matter how many people
但是不管是多少人
He will not appear in the same field at the same time
他不會同時在一個場域當中出現
How can a multitude of peoples become what we are if we say
雜多的人民如何可能成為我們假如說
We want the sovereignty of democracy by democracy
我們要民主治民主的主權
This concept of sovereignty is similar to that of Aristotle
這個主權的概念就跟前面亞里斯多德
Talking about the ruling group is different
在講這個統治團體就不一樣
Well, at this time, this is what the Chinese have just encountered
那麼這個時候這也是中國人剛剛遭遇
A confusion in the concept of democracy
民主概念的時候的一個困惑
That is to say, what is the so-called principle of democracy in this democracy?
就是說這個民主民主所謂民主道理是什麼
what is the main reason
那個主道理是什麼
Then there is another topic at this time
那麼這個時候有另外一個議題
I spend a little time here
這個地方我花稍微一點時間
Then it will be a little bit more technical
那麼會比較技術性一點一點
The rise of the sovereign state coincided with the social contract
主權國家的興起跟社會契約是差不多同時
social contract earlier
社會契約還早一點
But the previous social contract was more religious
但是之前的社會契約是比較宗教式的
So we're not talking about the social contract today
所以我們今天不談社會契約
The concept of dominant country
主行國家的概念
What about the combination of the two concepts of the host country?
主行國家兩個概念的搭配呢
at hobbs
在霍布斯呢
Is a
是一個
I think it is an ideal theory
我認為是一個最理想理論
The most distributed and best system
最周延最好的一個系統
let's not talk
我們不要講好
that is
就是說
The most compact system
最整密的一個系統
Hobbes proposed the state of nature
霍布斯提出了自然狀態
i don't know how many guests
我不知道有多少來賓
Know
知道
but
但是呢
He presupposes equality
他是以平等為前提
This is a core concept
這是一個核心的一個概念
people are equal
人與人是平等的
in classical theory
在古典的理論當中
he is not equal
他不是以平等
people are different
人有差異性
and there is inequality
而且有不平等
Your ability to pursue mathematical knowledge is better than mine
你追求數學知識的能力比我要好
Your ability to pursue knowledge in the machine world is better than mine
你追求機界知識的能力比我要好
So you are born unequal
所以你跟天生不平等
So he is in a different field
所以他在不同的領域當中
he can win
他可以勝出
He can be in that field
他可以在那個領域當中
become a good one
變成好的卓越的一個
There is the same presupposition in politics
那在政治當中也有一樣的一個預設
But
可是
Hobbes' state of nature
霍布斯的這個自然狀態
very interesting premise of equality
非常有趣的以平等作為前提
but his equality
但是他的平等
not equality in the moral sense
不是道德意義底下的平等
so he is saying
那麼他是說
in a state of nature
在自然狀態當中呢
Although we have physical differences
雖然我們有物理上的差異
Not everyone has the same strength
每個人力氣不完全一樣
it is impossible not to accept
這是不可能不接受的
But each has a similar chance of killing everyone else
但是每個人消滅其他人的機率相近
destroy others
消滅其他人
That is to say, the strongest person
就是說最強的人
when he sleeps
他睡覺的時候
i could stone it to death
我可以用石頭把它打死
so he don't bully me
所以他不要欺負我
If you say it, you say it
如說講的就是說
if you tie me up now
假如你現在把我綁住的話
I can't run of course I obey you
我不能跑我當然服從你
But you want me to ask you to sleep
可是你要要求我在你睡覺的時候
I can't cut the rope and run away
我不能割斷繩子跑掉
this has to be justified
這個要有正當性
So one of Hobbes' premise is that
所以霍布斯的一個前提是說
everyone he destroys everyone else's heritage
每個人他消滅其他人的相承的
This created a generalized mutual fear
這個造成了一個普遍的互相恐懼
Then he is in an unstable state
那麼他不穩定的一個狀態
what about this time
這個時候呢
His natural state is called a state of war
他的自然狀態叫做戰爭狀態
Well, I don't think we'll talk much about this
那麼這個我想我們不多講
But people fight each other
但是呢人與人是互相為戰
But Hobbes told a
可是霍布斯講了一個
Maybe it's our modern reaction
也許是我們現代人的反應
He said the fear of death
他說怕死的恐懼
fear of death
fear of death
you are afraid to hate
你怕 恨死
you don't want you to sleep
你不希望你睡覺起來
you are already in heaven
你已經在天堂裡面
or face it in hell
或在地獄裡面對不對
Then he let hit this place
那麼他讓砸中這個地方
Please pay attention to this word
請大家注意這個字
That is to say, people who have not yet become a community
就是一般就是說還沒有變成是共同體的人呢
He is willing to follow the lead of reason
他願意按照理性的導引
To create a political community following the laws of nature
遵循自然法而去創造政治共同體
that's how it came
是這樣子來的
so hobbes
所以霍布斯
If we look at textbooks on the history of political thought in general
假如我們看一般的政治思想史的教科書
he will tell you
他會告訴你
he is the defender of absolutism
他是絕對主義的護衛者
There is no problem
是沒有問題的
But Hobbes' logic
可是霍布斯的邏輯
in many, many places
在非常非常多的地方
influenced modern concepts of democracy and liberty
影響到現代的民主以及自由的概念
This is the Paradox that I want to talk about today
這是我今天特別講要來談一下的Paradox
What about natural ratings?
那麼自然的評等呢
His important place is here
他重要的地方在這裡
He produced a democratic priority
他產生了一個民主的優先性
why
為什麼呢
This is the original text of Hobbes
這是霍布斯的原文
He said when people come together to build a nation
他說當人民聚在一起建立一個國家的時候
almost as soon as they party
幾乎就他們聚會
we get together and talk
我們聚起來談
how we protect ourselves
我們如何保護我們自己
right
對不對
Aware of this, it can be said that he is building a democracy
意識這一點就可以說他是建立民主制
people get together
人聚合在一起
he is a democracy
他本身就是民主制
Then from their resource meeting topics
那麼從他們資源聚會議題來
They are said to be subject to the
他們被看說是受制於經由
is a decision that is agreed upon by the majority
是多數人同意所受的決定
And as long as this meeting lasts
而只要這種會議持續下去